MY HAPPY MARRIAGE
剧名:我的幸福婚约
EPISODE 11 MY MOTHER'S LEGACY
第11集:母亲遗留之物
I'll tell you everything.
我来告诉你事情经过
I'll tell you why Sumi married into the Saimori family,
澄美嫁入斋森家的原因
and why she sealed off your supernatural ability.
以及她封印你异能的原因
It was a few years before you were born.
那是你出生数年前的事了
Tsuruki Trading failed in negotiations with a certain leading client
鹤木贸易与某个大客户交涉失败
and were performing poorly.
业绩萎靡不振
Since we were backed by Tsuruki Trading,
我们家是受鹤木贸易支持的
we had a heavy debt load and were facing a predicament.
因此债台高筑 走投无路
That is when...
就在那时
the marriage proposal was brought to us.
有人向我们家求亲
They had heard from somewhere that the Usuba family was in crisis.
他们听说薄刃家出现危机 难以为继
They said they would pay off our huge debts
声称如果能娶到澄美
if Sumi married their son.
就可以替我们偿还债务
They were persistent, sending offers frequently.
他们再三纠缠
I rejected each offer.
我都回绝了
But one day...
但是有一天
Sumi accepted their offer on her own without consulting me.
澄美没有与我商量就接受了条件
Do you realize what you have done?
你知道自己在做什么吗?
It will mean that we'll be giving the Usuba blood to another family.
你这样会把薄刃家的血脉送给其他家
If we don't do anything at all, it's over for the Usuba family.
如果我们坐以待毙 薄刃家就完了
Sumi! You don't understand anything.
澄美 你什么都不懂
What do you think you'll be able to do with such a frail body?
你这样的身体 你以为你能做什么?
This is the only way forward.
除此之外 别无他法
Father, I'm sorry.
父亲 对不起
You're such a fool, my child.
你这个傻孩子
The family she married into was the Saimori family.
澄美嫁入的就是斋森家
After the finalization of this contract we call "marriage,"
在名为婚姻的“契约”成立之后
they cut off our means of communication with her.
他们切断了联系手段
As a result,
结果而言
our family ties were broken.
我们和澄美断绝了关系
Miyo.
美世
I have something I want to show you.
我有样东西要给你看
You possess the ability of Dream-Sight.
因为你有梦见的异能
Even Sumi didn't develop that supernatural ability.
就连澄美也没有这种力量
Dream-Sight?
梦见?
Go ahead and touch that tree.
碰一下这棵树试试
This woman from the Usuba family...
虽说这女人来自薄刃家
she's not very friendly.
也太冷淡了
Shinichi.
真一
This is not just a political marriage.
这不是单纯的政治婚姻
You do understand your role, don't you?
你明白你的使命吧?
Yes.
是
To conceive a child with her family's supernatural ability.
我一定会让她生下 拥有薄刃异能的孩子
I'm counting on you, Sumi.
就靠你了 澄美
You did it!
干得好
This girl.
这个孩子
She has the ability of Dream-Sight.
拥有梦见的异能
Haven't you confirmed it yet?
还不能确定吗?
No. Well, Miyo is still an infant.
是 美世还小
If we don't quickly obtain the Usuba family's supernatural abilities,
如果不能获得薄刃的异能
the Saimori family will be downgraded.
斋森家会被降格
We went through the trouble of getting their bloodline.
我们好不容易得到了薄刃的血脉
And there's no telling when she'll fall ill.
那个女人不知道什么时候就会死掉
If Miyo's no good, she must hurry to have another child.
如果美世不行 就让她再生一个
Yes.
遵命
I'm sorry, Miyo.
对不起 美世
I don't have much time left.
我已经没有多少时间了
Your supernatural ability
你的力量
will be discovered when the time comes.
会随着你长大而越加明显
Then your ability of Dream-Sight
你的梦见异能
will be misused by this family, and the Usuba family will...
会被这个家利用殆尽 薄刃家...
You will have to live on your own from now on.
今后你必须一个人生存下去
You might encounter sadness and hardships.
你可能会经历悲伤 尝尽艰辛
You might wonder why you don't have any supernatural abilities.
也许会因为没有异能而自责
But for now, let me seal off your ability.
但现在让我封印你的力量
I'm sorry, Miyo.
对不起 美世
You could see it, couldn't you?
你也看到了吧
At first, it may be difficult for you to accept it.
虽然你一开始可能难以接受
It's best for you to rest your body for now.
先休养身体
Damn. They just keep on coming.
可恶 没完没了
Godo, at this rate we'll...
五道 我们还是...
Don't give up so easily! We have to withstand it somehow!
不要说丧气话 我们必须坚持住
Commander!
队长
All of you!
你们所有人
I want to commend you for holding out.
你们能撑到现在 做得很好
We won't just leave you here and die, Commander.
我们不能丢下队长去死
The reconnaissance unit reports
据侦查部队报告
most of the band of Grotesqueries have already been exterminated.
异形的大部队已经清理干净了
Let's proceed to get rid of the rest of them all at once!
我们要一口气干掉残存的异形
- Yes, sir!
-遵命
Let's go!
我们上
Y-Yes...
请进
Good morning, Miyo.
早安 美世
How are you feeling?
你感觉如何?
Your supernatural ability is not acting up anymore, is it?
你的异能没有继续暴走了
Even if you don't tell me,
就算你什么都不说
your healthy complexion is proof.
你的脸色也说明了一切
By the way, please wear these clothes while you are here.
对了 以后你在这里就穿这些吧
A robe for the maiden of Dream-Sight,
这是薄刃家代代相传的
handed down through generations of the Usuba family.
为梦见的巫女特别制作的衣服
As for the clothes you were wearing, I will keep them for you, so don't worry.
你之前穿的衣服放在我那里 请不必担心
I was released from my nightmares, and my body was making a recovery.
我不再做噩梦 身体也逐渐恢复
But as time went by in this small birdcage,
在狭小的鸟笼之中 时间不断流逝
my feelings for my husband-to-be and my regrets
我对老爷的思念
were getting stronger by the day.
还有后悔 日渐增长
I should have told him the answer I decided long ago.
答案早就在我心中
It was completely my own fault.
这是我自作自受
Aren't you going to eat, Miyo?
你不吃吗 美世?
You still can't forgive me?
你还是不肯原谅我吗?
Or do you have a problem with your room?
还是说 你不喜欢这个房间?
Maybe the food wasn't to your liking.
是食物不合口味吗?
I'll get you something else right away.
我让人立刻重做
That's not it.
不是的
I'm stumped. What's the matter, then?
这就很头疼了 那到底问题出在哪里呢?
I want you to give me back my cherry blossom kimono.
请把樱花色的和服还给我
It's my precious kimono that my husband-to-be gave me.
那是老爷送给我的 对我很重要的衣服
I can't do that.
那可不行
Is it not possible at all?
无论如何都不行吗?
No.
是
I want to talk to my husband-to-be again.
我想再和老爷好好谈谈
Why?
为什么?
Because I was wrong about everything.
因为我觉得一切都不对
I'm ashamed to face him.
我无颜见他
But I think I should apologize to him in earnest, and...
但是我要跟他认真道歉 然后...
Do you want to leave this house?
你想要离开这里吗?
We will not allow that.
这可不行 你知道我们...
Listen, do you know how desperately I waited for you?
不 你知道我等了你多久吗?
Do you know how much happiness I'm feeling now?
你知道我现在有多幸福吗?
You don't know.
你不知道
I want to protect you.
我想要保护你
Why?
为什么?
Because it's my job.
因为这是我的职责
Please.
求你了
All I want to do is to see him.
我只是想要见老爷一面
I want to see him and tell him what I couldn't but I should have said.
我想见他 把没说出口的话告诉他
We've been adhering most faithfully to the code of our ancestors.
我们忠实地遵守着祖先定下的规则
We cannot use our real family name.
不能使用真正的姓氏
We are permitted to marry only within our kin.
只能从亲族之中选择结婚对象
We cannot have close friends or romantic partners.
不能有亲近的朋友或恋人
The Usuba family's duty
薄刃家的义务
is to subjugate the out-of-control supernatural ability possessors.
就是讨伐失控的异能者
But that has never been asked of us since I was born.
但从出生起 我从未接到这样的指令
No matter how much we adhere to the code, it means nothing.
无论如何忠于规则始终毫无意义
There will never be a day when we accomplish the duties of the Usuba family.
因为履行薄刃职责的那一天不会到来
I want a role that is all my own.
我想要只属于自己的职责
When a maiden of Dream-Sight appeared,
当梦见巫女现世时
a member of the family with supernatural abilities
会从族中选出一个异能者
was chosen to protect the maiden with their life, it is said.
用生命保护巫女
In the present day, that would be my role.
现在来看 那个人是我
Presumably, doubling as your spouse.
而且我也会成为你的伴侣
I beg of you, Miyo. Please stay here with us.
求你了 美世 留在这里
I want to protect you.
我想保护你
I don't want to cede this mission to anyone else.
我不会把这份使命交给别人
I thought...
我觉得
you were the same as me.
你和我是同类
Someone who had lost the purpose to live and was feeling hollow, like me.
曾经失去活下去的意义 和我一样空虚
Miyo.
美世
We did it!
成功了
We defeated the band of Grotesqueries!
我们击退了这群异形
Victory is ours!
我们赢了
Godo. Turn the battle formation back to the initial position.
五道 将阵型变回初期配置
We'll regroup the search unit.
将搜查部队再次收编
Yes, sir!
遵命
Huh?
什么?
Godo!
五道
- Commander!
-队长
How do you like living here?
这里的生活怎么样?
Are you experiencing any inconvenience?
有任何不便吗?
No, not particularly.
不 并没有
Um, is it utterly impossible for me to see my husband-to-be?
请问 我真的不能见老爷一面吗?
I'm sorry, but I just can't let you do that.
抱歉 只有这个不行
I don't mind if it's just once.
一次也行
Please.
求求你
Your stubbornness reminds me of Sumi.
你的顽固和澄美一模一样
If only I hadn't...
那时
been so cruel to cut her off.
如果我没放走澄美
I probably wouldn't have lost my daughter so early,
我也不会早早地白发人送黑发人
and you, my granddaughter, wouldn't have led such an unfortunate life.
你的人生也不会被扭曲吧
For all your hardships through the years,
这么多年让你吃了不少苦
I apologize.
对不起
Essentially, we are a family related by blood.
我们本来是以血脉相连的家族
If anything happens to you, we will come to help and support you.
如果你有不测 我们会帮助支持你
From now on, I want you to rely on us without hesitation.
从今往后 希望你不要客气 依靠我们吧
I don't know what to say, being suddenly told I'm part of your family.
你突然说我是你的家人 我不能接受
Even if you want me to, I don't know how to rely on you.
就算你让我依靠你们 我也不知道该怎么做
To begin with, what is a family?
说到底 家人到底是什么?
I don't even know that.
我连这个都不知道
People must think I'm strange.
大家都会讨厌我吧
I angered my husband-to-be.
我还惹老爷生气
Um, I'm very sorry to be telling you meaningless things.
对不起 说了些没有用的话
No, it's all right.
没关系
I'm glad you told me what you really think.
我很高兴能听到你的真心话
Just let me say something grandfatherly to you.
作为你的祖父 也让我说几句
As you said just now,
就像刚才这样
I think that sharing a burden you cannot carry by yourself is what a family does.
把自己的苦恼与人分享 这就是家人的意义
Sharing?
分享?
Relying doesn't mean leaving everything up to another person.
所谓依靠 不是将所有事都交给他人
I think it means asking someone to carry some of your load
而是把对于一个人来说 过于沉重的包袱
that you can't carry by yourself.
与他人一同承担
It's okay to disappoint them or anger them.
让他人失望或者生气也无所谓
The bond of a family won't be broken by something like that.
家人之间的牵绊 不会因为这点小事而断绝
Was it that way when my mother left this house?
母亲离开家也是如此吗?
It's true that I lost my temper at that time.
我当时确实怒不可遏
Didn't it make you hate my mother?
你不恨我母亲吗?
Of course, I didn't hate her.
当然不
I cared for her more than I felt it was unforgivable.
比起生她的气 我更关心她
Looking back, I regret it now.
事到如今 我很后悔
I misjudged what I should protect
我没明白我真正应该守护的事物
and because of that, I lost my beloved daughter.
因此失去了我宝贵的女儿
And Miyo,
而你
I care for you as much as I did for your mother.
我也同样珍惜你
Me?
我?
Yes.
是的
Since Sumi got married then, you were born.
澄美嫁过去 生下了你
And our family was able to survive.
我们家族才得以存续
I feel great happiness
我能见到你
from meeting you like this.
我真的很幸福
I didn't know my grandfather was feeling the same way as I do.
祖父也和我一样呢
He said things that were not true to his heart,
他说了违心的话
which hurt someone important to him, and he regrets it.
伤害了重要的人 并为此后悔
And my mother wished me happiness when she...
而我的母亲希望我能幸福
Someday, the time will come...
有一天 这份力量
When your ability will become necessary.
会对你很重要
So...
所以...
Miyo,
美世
I love you.
我爱你
Mother...
母亲
Apparently, Sumi's seal has now been completely broken.
看来美世的封印已经完全解除了
Grandfather!
祖父
What is it?
怎么了?
I just received a message from the military.
军方传来消息
What? Are you saying that Kudo...?
什么?你说久堂他...
What's happened to my husband-to-be?
老爷怎么了?
Kiyoka Kudo was attacked by the Grotesqueries and collapsed.
久堂清霞被异形袭击 受伤倒下
I don't have the details.
我不清楚具体情况
He was injured during a maneuver and hasn't regained consciousness.
他在作战中负伤 昏迷不醒
Can't be...
怎么会这样?
Where do you think you're going?
你要去哪里?
Wait!
等一等
Let me go and see him!
我要去老爷那里
I... don't want to give up.
我不想放弃
I can't let you go.
我不会让你走
You can't stop me. I'm going at any cost.
我就算硬闯也要走
You have it wrong.
不是这样的
The one who is making you stay here is not me.
这个家里想留下你的人不是我
I made a deal with someone.
我和某个人做了交易
Arata!
新
I don't want to lie to Miyo anymore.
我不想对美世撒谎了
The one I made a deal with is Mikado.
我是和帝上做了交易
Our family had long wanted the maiden of Dream-Sight back.
为了达成薄刃家夺回梦见巫女的夙愿
Mikado agreed to help us.
帝上出手相助
In return, he said
作为回报
Miyo must not have contact with any other people with supernatural abilities.
薄刃家要禁止美世 与其他异能者有任何接触
He ordered us to completely hide the existence
他命令我们要完全隐藏
of the maiden of Dream-Sight.
梦见巫女的存在
Why?
为什么?
I don't fully understand what His Majesty is trying to do.
我不知道陛下想要做什么
But if you disobey his order, surely not only the Usuba family,
但是如果违抗命令
but also you will be severely punished.
不仅是薄刃家 你也会受到严惩
What...?
怎么会这样?
Grandfather!
祖父
I can't give you up.
我不会放弃你
Just as you can't give up Kiyoka Kudo.
就像你不会放弃久堂清霞
But I made a decision too.
但是我也下定决心了
You want to go see Kiyoka Kudo, right?
你想要去见久堂清霞吧?
What?
什么?
If I'm going to let you see him, I'm accompanying you.
作为交换 我和你一起去
Because I want to protect you.
因为我想保护你
My, my. What can I do?
还真是拿你们没办法
You two are both my precious grandchildren.
你们都是我宝贵的孙辈
Supporting you two is the role of a grandfather.
支持你们是祖父的职责
Well, go on.
去吧
Thank you very much.
谢谢您
Sir...
老爷
Please be alright.
请一定要平安无事
Why? Commander...
为什么?
Why did he have to get hurt instead of me?
为了我这种人 队长身负重伤
Sir!
老爷!
Miyo!
美世小姐
Oh, good, you came!
太好了 你来了
Sir...
老爷
You're alive...
你还活着
Since you two were apart, I was so worried.
我还担心你们分处两地
What if this was his final day and you weren't here?
见不到最后一面
What would I do?
我都不知道该怎么办了
Hazuki.
叶月姐
He will wake up.
老爷肯定
I know he will.
会醒过来
I will never give up.
我绝对不会放弃
Miyo, you possess the power that could awaken Kiyoka Kudo...
美世 你应该能让久堂清霞醒来
the supernatural ability of Dream-Sight.
如果依靠你梦见的异能
My supernatural ability...
我的异能?
I can't say for sure,
我不能保证
but I think it's worth trying.
但是值得一试
I'll do it.
我会做的
If that is what I can do.
只要我能帮得上忙
Subtitle translation by: Ikuko Ohno
字幕翻译:郭宁